Cool. Hello everyone and uh welcome to
lecture 3 of CME 295.
Um so today is a very exciting day
because we're going to finally introduce
large language models. Uh but I guess
before we go into that I'm just going to
start traditionally with uh some
announcements. Um so some of you wanted
to have the slides before the class. So
just a heads up that in case you want to
use the slides to do some annotations
uh they're on the website right now. So
feel free to get them and uh with
Shervin we'll try to just on a regular
basis every Thursday evening have them
published on the website so that you can
download them and annotate.
Cool. So with that, let's start. And as
usual, we're going to recap uh last
week's episodes.
So if you remember, you know, lecture
one and lecture two were all about
introducing the concept of self
attention and linking them to the
construct of the transformer. And what
we did last lecture was look at all the
types of models that there are out there
and how they were all based on the
transformer.
So there are three categories, three
main categories of models. So the first
one that we saw was encoder decoder
model which basically relies on the
transformer. It has the encoder of the
transformer, the decoder of the
transformer and typically the tasks
there are input text. So text in text
out.
So we saw that one example was T5 and
all the variations.
The second type of model is where we
remove the decoder from the trans
transformer and we obtain an encoder
only model.
So uh we went uh deeper into BERT which
is the typical encoder only model and uh
I guess we also saw that what BERT has
is this nice property that it's encoded
embeddings are very meaningful and
expressive of the inputs and so yeah we
saw like the example of classification
sentiment extraction. So what we did was
in particular um take into consideration
the encoded embedding of the CLS token.
So uh I guess in real life BERT is used
to encode documents to encode sentences
and we're going to see later in the
class how these models are useful.
And then last but not least, we have the
third category of models which is
decoder only. So we only keep the
decoder part of the transformer. And so
here we also do a little bit of a of a
modification. So we remove the cross
attention because we don't need it
anymore. We don't have an encoder. And
these kinds of models are text in text
out.
And so GPT is a very good example of
such models and actually most models
these days they're only like they are
decoder only.
So these are the three main kinds of
models that you can see out there.
So far so good for everyone.
Cool. So with that I'm going to
introduce the term LLM. So, LLM stands
for large language model. So, what is a
large language model? So, first of all,
a large language model is a language
model. So, a language model is a model
that assigns probability to sequences of
tokens.
So, in this case, our model always
predicts the probability of the next
token. So, it's in that sense a language
model.
But also a large language model is
large. So why is it large? So we're
going to see that these models they are
actually scaled up in terms of size. So
first of all in terms of model size. So
these days it's not uncommon to see
models on the order of hundreds of
billions of parameters.
But yeah, typically when we say LLM, we
say at least on the order of a billion.
These models, they've also been trained
on a huge amount of data. And here by
amount of data, we quantify that by the
number of tokens that they were
pre-trained with. And this is on the
order of magnitude of hundreds of
billions of tokens or even trillions of
tokens.
So I think the biggest one biggest ones
are like on the tens of trillions of
tokens. So it's like huge
training sets
and they're also large because they need
a lot of compute. So typically you need
a bunch of GPUs to make them work.
Although these days there's been a lot
of um optimizations to have them work on
uh consumerbased GPUs. So we're going to
see that later.
But an LLM is large according to these
categories.
So another thing that I want to point
out is that all these terminologies
they're relatively new. So um I remember
in 2018 19 there was nothing like there
was no real definition of an LM. I think
no one actually talked about LLMs in the
beginning maybe people talked about
LLMs. They included BERT,
but BERT is an encoder only model that
does not produce text. So with the
current definition of an LLM, which
right now has been pretty well
established, BERT would not be an LLM
because it doesn't produce text. So here
we only consider language models that do
textto text that are very large in size
in terms of amount of data they have
been trained on and in terms of compute.
Cool. And as we saw before these models
are decoder only. So here what we do is
we remove the encoder. We only keep the
masked self attention, the feed forward
neuronet network and then the you know
addition and normalization.
So we only keep this and this is the
backbone of LMS
and uh so I mentioned you know GPT is a
kind of a good example but it's not just
that you have plenty of other models. So
you may have heard of Llama from Meta,
Gemma from Google, uh Deepseek, Mistro
Quen, so on like the the list is long.
I would say roughly I mean more than 90%
of like modern day LLMs, they're all
decoder only. So I think that's uh
something to keep in mind.
Cool.
Um okay so now you know how LLMs are
made of but there is something else that
people these days also introduced to
these models and we're going to see that
in a bit
so I mentioned that these models are
huge in size again typically hundreds of
billions of parameters so it takes a lot
of compute to just compute one inference
or also to train these models.
But you may wonder, do you really need
to have all these parameters be
activated during a forward pass to make
a simple prediction?
So I'm going to u like have a little
metaphor. So let's suppose you enter in
a room and in the room there is a
mathematician,
a physicist, a chemist and a historian.
So you come in this class there's a
bunch of people who are expert in what
they do.
And you have a question, you have a math
question.
That's a question I have for you is who
would you ask your question?
Would you ask the mathematician? Would
you ask the chemist? Would you ask
everyone?
Well, right now we ask everyone. We ask
all parameters of the model to be
involved in the computation of uh you
know the generation.
And so the idea here is
given an input
maybe it's not necessary to ask everyone
to be involved in the computation. So
the idea is let's actually just have a
subset of the model be involved in the
computation of the next token.
So I'm just introducing this idea of
experts. So let's suppose we're
introducing uh the following notation.
So let's suppose we have n experts. So
think of it as your mathematician, your
chemist, historian, like whatever. So
these are your experts and the idea is
given an input X,
you're going to ask yourself
who should be involved in the generation
of the output.
So you're going to have let's say
another network. We're we're going to
call it G like gate but it's also
sometimes called router.
So let's suppose we have some gate that
tells us which expert should be involved
in the inference.
So if we have that so let's suppose here
the gate tells us okay so actually
expert number two is well suited to
answer your question. So here the idea
is that the input is just going to flow
into that expert
but not the other experts.
So this has a name. It's called mixture
of experts. So it's denoted.
Everyone talks about so these are
mixture of experts. And so the formula
that you will see a lot is this one. So
the output y which is denoted yhat is
the sum of the expert output
weighted by some quantity which is the
output of the gate which tells you how
important the output of each expert is.
Yeah,
great question. So question is how do
you train G? How do you train E? So
typically you train them jointly.
So we're going to see that maybe in a
yeah a little later, but you can think
of it as you know just training as
usual. You do your forward pass, you
compute the last and you back prop.
And it's actually an interesting
question because there is some
challenges that come with training emois
that we're going to see in a second.
Yep.
Uh question is uh what are these E what
is the architecture of these E? So let's
suppose right now that they're just some
network. We're not specifying them for
now but we're going to see this in a
second. Let's suppose for now it's like
some network.
Cool.
Okay, so I told you that you know what
if we don't activate everyone? What if
we activate a subset? But this formula
actually
um I guess assumes that we're actually
considering all expert outputs. So I
just want to distinguish two kinds of.
So there's one kind that is called a
dense.
So dense MO actually does not have any
constraints on the number of experts
that are involved.
So these weights they can be anywhere
between zero and one. So think of them
as a probability distribution
but it's just going to put more weight
towards some experts compared to others.
So back back to the example that I had.
So let's suppose I have a math question.
So I'm going to ask the mathematician,
the chemist, the historian. So I'm
probably going to add a higher weight to
what the mathematician says compared to
let's say the historian. So this is the
idea.
But then the interesting thing is when
we constrain the number of experts that
are activated because here as we
mentioned previously what we're
interested in is to not involve everyone
is to make some savings in the amount of
compute that we do. So there's a second
kind of MOE that's called the sparse MOE
and what it does is it only selects the
quoteunquote top K experts.
So K can be equal to one. So one expert
or even two. So it's a hyperparameter
that you choose. And so here the
expression of the output becomes the sum
over all the chosen experts of uh g of x
time e of x.
So far so good.
Cool. Uh and of course there's a lot
more to it. So in case you are
interested in learning more uh feel free
to go into the resources that are at the
bottom of the slide. Um so one thing
that I will say is that we have a unit
of measure of the amount of compute that
these models produce for each uh each
pass. So you will see the term flops. So
have you have you seen the term flops
out there?
No not really. So it stands for floating
point operations.
So it quantifies how many operations
like think of it as like additions,
multiplications
are involved in a forward pass let's say
and it basically quantifies how compute
heavy is your task.
So typically what we say is when we go
through a sparse MO as opposed to a
dense MOE we have a lower amount of
flops.
So this is the unit of measure that you
will see.
But back to your question. So what are
these experts?
So if you remember I mean 10 minutes ago
we said that LLMs they are decoder only
models.
So I have a question for you. Let's
suppose we wanted to put some
in our LLM.
Where would would we put it?
So here I guess we have three choices.
We have uh the mass self attention
layer. We have the feed for neural
network and then we have like this
normalization. So question for you I
guess where would you put this?
I guess where do you think
is I guess the most complex part of the
network? Where is there a lot of
operations
feed forward? Yes. Yeah. Great great
answer. So uh it's indeed the feed
forward neuron network
and the reason for that is I think
Shervin mentioned it I think in lecture
one. So if you remember the feed for
neural network is a network such that
you have the input which is your you
know dd dimensional input vector and
then you have uh this being projected
into let's say dfff dimensional space
and then it goes back to the dd
dimensional
um I guess uh space. So the DFF
is typically larger than your
dimension of I guess the input. When I
say input is here. So it's typically
larger. So
the amount of parameters that you have
in that feed for null network is
something on the order of magnitude of D
model time D FFF
time 2 plus some bias. So it's basically
your order of magnitude and
the attention layer if you think about
if you remember it's basically composed
of the projection matrices.
What is the dimension of the projection
matrices? So it's the model times the
dimension of keys, the dimension of
queries, the dimension of values.
And this dimension is typically much
lower.
So think of it of hundreds.
So your D model is typically O of 100, O
of a,000
and then the projection here the DFF
is O of a,000 or of 10,000.
Cool. So is everyone now convinced that
this is a good way good place to put the
mixture of experts?
Yeah.
Cool. So this is actually how it's done.
So in modern day day LLMs this idea of
not involving everyone in the
computation of the next token prediction
is such that you would put put the
mixture of experts where the FFN is
which is basically here
and typically you would have a sparse
mixture of experts meaning that so back
to your question so these experts are
feed for neural network. So you would
you would have several networks that you
can train but you would only activate
one.
So typically K would be equal to one. It
can be also equal to two but it would
only be a subset. So that's my point. Um
and this routing would be done at the
token level.
So if you remember you know the decoder
it basically takes uh something as
input. So you know a bunch of tokens
and here what I'm saying is that each
token will be processed by an expert
that may be different from the other
token.
So the router router here would take
the representation of the token as input
and figure out which expert should be
best for this token to flow towards.
Does this idea make sense?
So I have a little um illustration later
on that hopefully will help.
So now back to your question about how
you train this model like do you train
the router separately do you train the
expert separately. So one challenge that
people have is when they train these
based models
to make sure that all experts
are I guess having a weight are being
used
because it's very possible that you
train your model and that somehow only I
don't know one or two experts always get
activated
and the other one they always are
inactive. They're never involved in the
computation.
So this problem is called routing
collapse. So why is it called routing
collapse? Is because a router always
chooses some experts but not others.
So this is a challenge and the way
people try to mitigate this challenge is
by changing the loss function
and adding it some extra term which is
written here.
So it's basically some hyperparameter
alpha
times the number of experts
times the sum of quantities that depend
on whether or not tokens went to a
certain expert I and then summed over
all experts.
So it's not super important that you
completely understand exactly how that
formula works. The only thing that I
think you should take away from this
slide is that this extra loss
allows these quantities
to converge more towards uniform
distributions. So what are these
quantities just as a reminder? So f of I
is the fraction of tokens that are
routed to expert I
and P of I is the average routing
probability for expert I.
So when I say that, you know, all
experts should be used kind of the same,
what I'm saying is I want this
probability to be kind of uniform
across experts.
Yeah.
Yeah. So the question is uh I guess uh
when do you compute this quantities? So
yeah like you can think of it as like
you know regular training uh process
like you know you do some like mini
batch you kind of like go go go through
that through like the the model and then
you compute all these quantities and
then what you do is you do your um your
back propagation based on that and I
guess what I want you to remember is
that this incentivizes
the probability
um I guess the the choice of the router
to be more uniform across experts which
is something that mitigates this routing
collapse phenomena.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. So the question is can we use
dropout? Of course you can always like
bundle that with some other techniques.
So people have just kind of found this
to be very helpful. So speaking of other
techniques, there is something that I've
not talked about which is very similar
to the dropout um idea. So it's called
noisy gating.
Noisy gating is basically uh you have
your
your predictions from the gates but then
you add some noise to it.
So basically it you know by pure chance
it just allows other experts to be
involved in the computation. So it's
also some other technique. There's a
bunch of techniques but yeah dropout is
uh indeed quite useful for like things
like overfeeding and the idea can be
reused in in different settings.
Yep.
So the question is how can you so you
mean differentiable?
So here I guess how do you take the
derivative is that your your question?
Uh how is that? So can you explain a bit
more what your concern is?
>> Mhm. So I guess uh to this question um
so the average routing probability
so that one is a function of the gate
output right that's one pi
right so I guess your question is for fi
for fi
okay I don't have a good answer on top
of my head but I think like people have
some techniques and these days you know
you just don't even have to do this by
hand. You have uh like the built-in
thing. Um so maybe I can follow up with
you for fi, but for P of I, do you see
that this one is is quite clean? It's
just the average of uh the probabilities
from the gates.
Uh yeah. So basically the probability
the output probability from the the gate
you can think of it as just the vector
being projected on a space of n where n
corresponds to your number of experts
and then it's gone through softmax. So
your output is basically summing up to
one
and each of these dimensions they
represent the value corresponding to
what expert I would be I guess used for
like for instance the first dimension
would be for expert one second dimension
for expert two and so on. So you just
take the average of this and like this
one you can express it from you know all
the parameters. So I think you should be
you should be fine with that one. Yeah.
So the question is if we increase the
number of moes does it increase the
number of model parameters. So it's a
great question. So it's actually
actually one of the ideas behind MO
based models which is that you can scale
the model without having to incur the
cost of having significantly more
compute at inference time.
So you can increase so people say
capacity can increase your the capacity
of your model but you will still keep
some I guess like control the amount of
active parameters and active parameters
are the parameters that are that are
used for a forward pass. So yeah people
just kind of use that. So yeah it will
just increase the number of parameters.
So that's why you see some MO based
models that are even bigger than the
ones that we kind of had like on the
order of hundreds of billions. We even
have on the order of trillions of
parameters. So for instance here uh one
reading I I recommend is switch
transformer
which scaled up to 1 something trillion
parameters. So yes, definitely more
uh but that being said, so if you read
the paper, you will also see that these
models there are more what they call
sample efficient.
So they take less time
to be as good as what the model would
have been with a lower number of
parameters. So if you look at like if
you draw the you know training training
curve as a function of like the training
time you see that these models they're
typically more sample efficient.
Sorry.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. Everything here is
a trade-off. Everything here is a
trade-off.
>> Yeah. Cool. Yeah.
Um, so the question is each attention
head will have a number of experts. So
it's actually regardless of the
attention heads. So the attention heads
are you can think of them as being like
independent you know something else and
the number of experts is independent of
that.
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
Right. Right.
All right. Yeah. The question is whether
every block will have a number of extra.
The answer is yes. And typically those
weights are not shared.
So typically you So actually we're going
to see an example. Um it can very well
be that layer one there is the expert
number I don't know three that was
chosen but layer two there is like
expert number one. And you know it's
it's like it's all free. It's trainable.
So the so the question is we will decide
where to uh where expert will go to. So
all of that is decided by the gates
which is this quantity.
Everything is uh decided by the gates
which has trainable weights. So you can
think of this as just some projection
from the input x to an n dimensional
space where n is the number of experts.
Uh so question is at what point during
the inference is it decided? So um let's
suppose we're at inference time. I'm
going to walk you through how it works.
So you have your x.
So you have this you know attention
mechanism. So it interacts with all
tokens from the past given that it's
decoder only. So it's like the masked
and it goes here and at the beginning of
the fit for neural network block the
token is of course contextual. So it has
the information from like these other
tokens because it's attended. And what
it does is it goes here.
So X first goes into G.
G computes uh this you know probability
distribution over all experts and given
here that we are in a sparse MOE setting
we will only choose the top K. So let's
suppose it's the top one just the
highest uh probability
um and you will you will know which
expert this one will be and so as a
result of that you will only compute the
the output value of the expert that the
input was chosen.
Mhm. So can you elaborate on that
actually?
Yeah.
At what point exactly? So it's after the
self attention layer.
Yeah.
Uh so the question is do we have
different classification for different
heads? No. So there's only one router.
So uh I think I I understand your
question. So your question is what do
you do given that you have different
attention computations going on in
parallel with the heads. So if you
remember the attention layer has these
different heads but at the end of it
what it does is it concatenates all the
results from each of these heads and
then projects it once again in the D
model space.
Yep.
Yes. So the question is do we have
different G's? So the only thing I can
tell you is that the G is just layer
specific. It's layer specific. It's
trainable. So it's basically going to
learn how to process all these uh
inputs. So the G the only thing I can
tell you for for your question is is
going to be layer specific. So the G is
going to be one G for let's say the
first layer, another G for the second
layer and so on. And that one is going
to be trained.
Cool.
Great. Looking at the time. Do we have
any other questions here?
We're good.
Perfect.
So now I just wanted to show you a cool
thing that um I believe uh the Mistral
uh team was showing in one of their
papers. So what they were showing here
was for a given piece of text
to show in which expert each token was
routed.
So as we noted before um
so experts are different from one layer
to another. So I believe here it's yeah
for layer zero so it's like for one
given layer and we do see that
you know roughly these tokens I guess
they leverage
like a uniform amount of experts more or
less.
What you would not want to see is to
have every token be the same color, but
luckily it is not.
But yeah, so that's one cool way of just
representing how the routing is done is
to just have your input text and just
represent where each token in which
expert each token went.
Cool. Okay.
So what we just saw was
one way that modern day LMS
change their architecture to incorporate
the fact that we may want to scale the
model but not increase the computation
complexity for one forward pass and we
saw that with
so you will see a lot of MOE based LLM
out there and now what we will
is
knowing that we have an LLM, we're going
to focus on
don't worry uh we're going to focus on
how a response is being generated.
So remember when I told you that you
know these uh modern day LLMs what they
do is they take some text in and they
have some text out. So it's typically
this task of next token prediction. So
you have a token in so let's say
beginning of sentence you go through
your llm and it just uh generates the
next word or the next token so a and
then you take a and it goes to teddy and
then teddy bear is etc etc
but so far we have never really dug into
exactly how we chose the next token.
So what we're going to do right now is
to see exactly how we're generating the
next token.
So as you know here our LM is just a
decoder only architecture. So here what
you have is a decoder with your input
here and then your output there.
So let's suppose for a second that we
know everything that's happening in the
middle and we're just obtaining
output probabilities
that are going to look a little bit like
this.
So given a token or some sequence of
token as inputs, you have an output
probability distribution that represents
what the model thinks is the likelihood
that there will be a next token let's
say that is equal to a to airplane to
fluffy etc.
So this is what you have.
So now my question to you is
if we told you we have some sequence as
inputs and we want to choose the next
token
and if I told you that our model is
giving out actually a probability
distribution.
I guess how would you choose the next
token based on this?
Sorry.
Great. The token with maximum
probability
there. Okay. Great. So yeah, the first
idea, let's just take the token with
highest probability.
So,
so it's a very natural approach, but I'm
not sure if you've been using things
like chat GPT or Gemini. Every time you
ask something, it always responds it
responds something that is slightly
different,
right? So if you always choose the token
with the highest probability
given that the computation here we're
going to see is all deterministic
what that means is you're always going
to generate the same thing regardless of
uh I guess with the same input right so
that's one one limitation so it's not
very like diverse
the second problem is
if you choose
the highest probability token on a I
guess iterative basis.
You're locally optimal, but you're not
necessarily globally optimal.
So what does that mean? So I guess if
you think about it, our objective is for
us to produce a sequence, an output
sequence of tokens that is, I guess, of
a high probability.
But the problem is if you always choose
the highest probability token, you will
not necessarily obtain the highest
probability sequence.
Are you convinced of this statement by
the way? So let me give you an example.
So let's suppose you have the next token
where one token is8 the other one is 7
and then you choose to go with the 08.
No actually it's not 7 because it has to
sum to one. So let's say 02. So let's
suppose if you go ahead with the
sequence that that starts with the 08.
Let's suppose all other token
probabilities are very low.
Basically you will have an output
sequence that will have a lower
probability than let's say the other
path which would let's suppose have
higher probability predictions in the
later steps.
Right? So we're going to see this in a
second, but this is the idea. So if you
choose the highest predicted
probability, it's a good first idea, but
it's locally optimal, but not
necessarily globally optimal.
And this is the reason why we have a a
second method
that is about keeping track of the K
most probable path.
So I'm not sure if you've heard of beam
search. So that's what beam search does.
So here K is sometimes called the beam
size or the beam width. So if you hear
these terms, these are just names that
are given to the number of path that we
keep track of. And so this works as
follows.
So let's suppose we start our generation
with the beginning of sentence token.
we want to figure out what the next
token is. So let's suppose we have uh
here in this example very basic example
like three tokens
and let's suppose the two highest
probable tokens are a and z.
So if we have k equal to two what we're
going to do is to keep track of these
two branches.
So that's the first iteration.
The second iteration is we're going to
look at all the probabilities
of next token prediction for these two
tokens
and we're going to always
save the two most probable path and here
for instance let's suppose if it's like
the and then fluffy and then a and cute.
So back to what I was saying later uh
earlier. So what I was saying was here
if you were choosing the path that went
along the highest probability token path
like the the
it's very much possible that the highest
probability token after the would be a
much lower probability than the one
after a.
And so this is what beam search tries to
do. tries to have a more globally
optimal solution. So let's suppose we
continue that and then at the end of the
day we obtain
uh I guess a number of uh potential I
guess choices uh and the k potential
choices and then we we pick the one that
is the kind of highest likely the
sequence with the highest probability.
So people typically what they do is they
take the sum of the logarithm of the
probabilities of the token. So they they
what they say is they say uh okay so the
log probability of the sequence is the
sum of the log probability of each next
token prediction. So it's the log
probability of a uh knowing bos and and
then cute knowing boss and a and so on
and so forth.
But I just want to point out one
limitation of this approach which is
that
the more you generate tokens
the lower
your I guess uh end sequence probability
will be
because if you think about it you know
all these probabilities they're between
zero and one. So think of it like in the
kind of multiplied sense. So let's
suppose you have the probability of the
whole sequence
which is just a multiplication of the
probability of the next token.
The more you add probabilities be below
like less than one,
the more this quantity will I guess go
towards zero.
So I guess uh this method as is
will prioritize sequences that are
shorter
and so for that reason beam search has
some uh additional term that basically
counteracts that that effect. So
something on the order of like one over
number of tokens to the power of
something. So in practice there's some
uh technique to make sure that you know
things kind of work relatively well.
But okay let's suppose we figure out all
these things. Uh the problem is that we
need to keep track of this most probable
path. We need to do all this uh kind of
uh saving etc. And it just like requires
a lot of computation.
And the other thing is we're still
interested in the most probable path
which basically will lead to a sequence
that is you know very that the model
thinks is very likely
but sometimes what you want is for your
output to be more diverse or more
creative.
So that's why beam search is actually
not something that people typically use.
People use beam search for things like
machine translation where you actually
need to have something that is close to
uh something being very likely but
actually people use a third method
and this method is called also the
sampling method. So I told you we have a
probability distribution over tokens
regarding what the next token should be.
And so what people do is they just
sample the next token
using that probability distribution.
Does this make sense?
So in this example, uh fluffy, gentle,
kind, and let's say smart will have a
higher probability of being drawn as
opposed to let's say airplane and wear
that have a lower probability of
occurring. nonzero probability but they
have a probability of occurring.
Cool.
Any questions so far?
Yep.
Right. Uh so the question is it's not
for training, it's for inference. Yes.
Correct. So this is the you can think of
it as response generation. So let's
suppose you have your model that is
trained. What you want is to generate an
output. So what would you do?
Yeah.
So I guess just to complete my answer.
So during training what you would do is
care about the output probabilities and
then compare them with the actual label
uh which is most of the time like a hard
label. Uh and yeah this is what you
would compare. So this one is let's
suppose you have an LLM that is trained.
How would you generate a response?
Cool.
Everyone good?
Yeah.
Yep.
Yeah. So question is how do you do
sampling in this situation? So actually
my next slides but I just want to make
sure everyone was uh on the same page
regarding just the intuition.
So highest probability is called greedy
decoding is probably not something that
we want.
Beam search is a little bit better. It's
more something that is globally optimal.
It's not globally optimal, but more
towards that. So, it's better, but it
lacks diversity. It lacks creativity,
which is why what we want to do is to
actually sample
each token.
Um, and I guess we have a few methods
that um also restrict
the kinds of tokens that we want to
sample from. because I mentioned you
know these very low probability tokens
they can still I theoretically be
sampled but it's not necessarily
something that we want.
So what people do is they typically
restrict the highest probability tokens
and only sample from them. So you may
have heard of this term top K sampling.
Who has heard of this term? Yeah, a
little bit. Okay. So, what you do is you
select the top
highest probable K. So, the top K
highest probable tokens and you sample
from them. So, let's suppose if K is
equal to four, you take the highest four
highest probable and then you just
sample with them. And there's something
else that is quite similar in idea which
is called top P.
So top P is that you limit yourself to
the top to the highest probable tokens
such that their cumulative probability
is more than a threshold P.
So again it will do the same thing. It
will select the highest probable um
tokens.
But then there is a part that I still
left out.
which is how do you obtain these
probabilities to start with.
So if you remember
here I had mentioned that we just assume
we have the probabilities we just have
them and we want to choose what the next
token is.
But now the question that I'm asking is
now that we know what we will do with
these probabilities. I guess one
question is how do you obtain these
probabilities to start with?
So if you remember
these
transformerbased architecture basically
computes an encoded representation of
the input.
And what you have is some final layers
at the very top of the figure which aims
at projecting
the vector into the space of the
vocabulary
because what you want to do is to have a
probability number for how probable it
is for you to sample a given token.
Right? So here what you would do is at
the very top of the of the architecture
have your uh input which is your encoded
embedding of the token go through a
linear layer which basically projects
your dmodel vector into a space of
dimension
size of v.
And of course what you want is
probability. So you would have a softmax
layer which basically converts
everything to probabilities such that
everything sums to one
and in order to compute the
probabilities
this is the formula that you would use
which is the softmax layer. So there is
a a hyperparameter that is quite
important that I want to talk to you
about which is the temperature T.
And so this is where it uh pops up. So
you have the probability of
the next token being a given word which
is equal to the exponential of the input
respect to that given word over
temperature. And then you normalize that
by the sum of all the other exponential
of the quantity over t.
And now what we're going to see is what
that t is used for or what that t
actually uh does in practice.
So before we go into that just one
question has anyone heard about
temperatures when it comes to response
generation?
Yeah. Cool. So hopefully that will kind
of give you a better idea of how the
temperature kind of influences your
output predictions.
So I guess the question that I want to
ask you is what would be the impact of
having a low temperature versus a high
temperature?
So low temperature would correspond to
diverse. Why?
Yeah.
Yeah. Has
anyone So we'll come to that in a
second. So yeah, do you have a
a lower temperature? Increase in
temperature. So I guess back to your um
the explanation about like uh I guess
lowering the temperature and what impact
it will do to the So I guess like do you
have a suggested uh response to that? I
guess like yellow temperature. Let's
suppose you have a lower temperature.
What happens?
Mhm.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So I guess um
so the long story short is low
temperature will create a spiky
distribution and then high temperature
will create a uniform distribution. But
I guess so I think you had the right
like intuition. Um
I'm going to maybe write this in more
mathematical terms.
So whoops. Okay. Um let's suppose you
have your probability
which is uh you know the exponential of
x i / t
over the sum of
exponential of xj / t.
So just mathematically you can actually
prove uh what is happening here. So
let's suppose you have the index of the
highest x i
So let's call that K.
So let's suppose what I do is I will
factor by this uh quantity. So actually
here I don't have space. So let's do
here. So it will be a e of
k
temperature and then here you have the
sum of over all j of exponential of x j
over t minus
x k / t.
So what I did is I just multiplied the
numerator and the denominator by
exponential of x k / t. So I multiplied
numerator and denominator and of course
they cancel out. But then what I have
here is xy - x k / t and here xj - ak
over t.
So when
I is equal to k,
this term is zero, right? is exactly
zero regardless of the temperature.
And here
xj minus a x k
is always negative or zero.
Right?
So here
if I is equal to k
you have
zero
over t. So here it's one
and then you have 1 +
I guess some quantity so j - x k / t
which is going to be negative
so t going to zero so that one will be I
guess
going to let's say minus infinity
so exponential of minus infinity is
zero.
So what you will end up with is
something where for i equal to k you
will have a nonzero
probability
but then for i not equal to k you will
have zero
over something that is not equal to zero
which is zero.
So just mathematically if you factor by
exponential of x k / t where k is the
index of the highest value uh I guess
the highest logit or the highest
activation vector
can actually show that for a small
temperature
only the highest
so the index of the I guess highest
um value will be the one that will be uh
I guess highest probable with a spike
there
and then when you have a high
temperature basically it will look like
a uniform distribution because all this
all these quantities so when t tends to
plus infinity this tends to zero so
exponential of zero is
just e sorry not uh one
>> it's one so it's one over the number of
J so it's one so just a uniform
distribution across all the tokens of
your vocabulary
yeah
um so the question is how can I
interpret a small
Mhm.
So the question is can I interpret that
as a gausian? I think so it's kind of
tough because gausian you have like some
continuous quantity as in the x-axis. So
here you have you know you have tokens
so it's kind of discrete and it's not
like uh something that you can order. So
just probably interpret that as small
temperature is very spiky. So you will
really have a given set of tokens that
are the highest probable that will
appear more.
And if you have a high temperature then
basically tokens even the ones that were
not uh there to be kind of the highest
probable will actually have an adjusted
probability that that would be higher.
Yes. So you can think of it as like some
kind of scaling in that sense. So long
story short, what I want to tell you is
if you have a small temperature, it will
encourage the next token to be
geared towards being the highest
probable token.
And then if if you have a high
temperature,
I guess the distribution of
probabilities will be kind of closer to
a uniform if you really increase that
temperature by a lot. So your output
will be more creative. You'll have
tokens that um you would have not drawn
that would be drawn.
And so what that means in practice if
you're I don't know if you're with your
favorite LLM and let's suppose you want
to uh I don't know write something very
creative.
So which one would you use? Would you
use a low temperature or high
temperature?
High temperature. Yes. So if you want
something that's more deterministic,
more I guess closer to uh something that
is very um I guess what you think would
be high quality, you will use more of a
lower uh temperature. So one note here
is that if you have
a strictly positive temperature,
every time you run your model over an
input,
you will obtain a different output.
Right.
So something I want to point out is
nothing in the transformer architecture
is probabilistic. Everything is
deterministic. The only thing that is
not deterministic is how you sample the
next token. It's the only thing that is
not deterministic.
So what will you do to have like a
deterministic output?
we have t equal to zero. t equal to
zero, you know for sure that your output
will be just one thing and nothing else.
Well, that's what is kind of a
theoretical
uh property. But in practice,
you have some stuff that is happening in
the computation that introduces some
nondeterministic
operations. So it's very much more
advanced than the scope of this class.
Much more advanced of the scope of this
class. I just want to call out that in
practice t equal to zero may lead to
different results because of this um
kind of practical piece. So what I
recommend so there's a suggested reading
in case you're completely optional. So
there's a very recent article around
defeating nondeterminism in LM
inference.
So I recommend that you read it in case
you're interested. So the high level
idea is
our GPUs, our hardware
when they reduce some of these
operations,
sometimes they are reducing numbers that
are on really different scales.
So the order at which these operations
are happening is actually quite
important.
So the idea is if these operations they
happen in different order it may lead to
different results. Even if in theory it
should be exactly the same in practice
it may not be the same. And this article
actually does a great job at just
explaining the intuition.
So yeah just if you're interested
completely optional.
Cool. Uh I know I'm kind of late. So I
guess um last thing that I want to say
is
let's suppose what you want to do is to
generate an output in a very specific
format. Let's suppose JSON JSON format.
So I guess a very naive approach would
be to tell your LLM well please generate
this in let's say JSON and then it
produces something and then you kind of
uh try to see if it's a valid JSON. If
it's not you repeat you just tell it to
generate again until it does something
well. So that's the first naive
approach.
Well there's a second approach that is
called guided decoding.
And what that does is during the
generation process,
it filters out what it calls invalid
next tokens.
So here uh let's suppose I want to
generate this JSON. I know for sure that
my first token must be uh something that
opens the you know the
I forgot what the English word was for
this but you know it just opens the the
brackets. Yeah, open the brackets. So
you can only have this and then you can
only have the property name it's and so
on and so forth and sometimes you can
have more than one permitted next token
in which case you would go back to our
you know next token strategy.
Yeah.
So the question is how do you restrict
uh the the other tokens? There's a bunch
of papers that go into that. We will not
cover this, but I can give you some
pointers. Uh just type finite state
machine FSM uh context grammar. So
there's a bunch of papers that do that.
We will not cover that here.
Cool. And I think with that we will uh
go to the second part uh with Shervin.
Great.
Thank you.
So uh now together we're going to look
at uh different prompting strategies. So
now that we know how responses are
generated, we're going to see how to get
uh responses and how to get great
responses.
So let's go back to our favorite example
about our cute teddy bear. Uh so just I
want to introduce one piece of
vocabulary. So when you have some kind
of input uh you have the length of your
inputs measured in number of tokens uh
and you will see in the literature that
it can have different names. So you can
uh see it called context length, context
size, window size and I think the latest
tools like if you code on you know
cursor or any other uh code assisted
tool I think they call it a more context
length but like all these terms are uh
equivalent
and they know the same thing. Okay.
So now I want to take some time to
discuss like what can be some orders of
magnitude here. So uh like modern day
LLMs they tend to be in the order of
magnitude of tens of thousands hundreds
of thousands or millions of input tokens
as inputs. So this is the kind of input
it can take. So sometimes you hear some
new LLM boast some number and then that
number of context length is exactly
that. So it's like how much tokens can
it accommodate in a single pass.
Okay, great. And then yeah the models
you have seen uh like maybe some like
advertisement of these models. So I
think like Gemini and others they're in
the million territory. Um and uh you
know does that mean it's all nice and
pretty? you know, do we if we have like
more context length, is it going to
solve everything?
Actually, not. There is a phenomenon
that was recently dubbed as context rot
in a paper from earlier this summer
where basically the authors are
experimenting the capacity of the model
to retrieve some piece of information uh
in a test called needle in a haststack.
So basically they ask some question and
in larger and larger pieces of text they
bury the answer and they they try to
look at the capacity of the model to
surface that answer and then you can see
that with respect to an increasing
context length that ability to ground
the information with the answer that is
in the context decreases
and yeah the paper I think is a very
interesting one. it like controls with
respect to what else is in the context
like there is a term of like distractors
where they like put some noise and then
they see distractors basically
contributes in decreasing the retrieval
capability. So you know also what is in
your context matters. Um, so this is why
in general when you have a retrieval
problem where you want to use your LLM
to solve it, you have some good
incentive to try to target as much as
possible the right piece of context for
your LLM to see and predict on.
Okay, great. And yep.
Yep. So the
Yes. So the question is uh is the
context length exactly what is shown
during self attention? Uh yes. Yeah. So
and then we're going to see so I think
we saw last time that uh sometimes there
are like some uh tricks that are used
for the like complexity of the self
attention mechanism not to be n squared.
So this is what is being used to uh like
manage basically the complexity of the
computations as the context length
grows. Yeah, but great call out that
that's exactly uh what is it about.
Okay, great. Any questions? Any other
questions?
Okay, great. Um so now let's define what
do uh prompts usually look like. So
there is no formal theory on how to
structure a given prompt but this is
these are the main lines that are
usually found in uh prompts presented to
models. So you can distinguish a part
that is uh like setting up the context
where you like just put the setting you
know you make it clear to the model what
you know kind of query you want to to
issue. Then uh let's say if you have
some task that you want the model to
perform, you have instructions and then
these instructions are like some sort of
function that take as input something.
So you add some inputs and uh in order
to get what you want out of the model's
response, you may want to add some
constraints out of it. So here we we
took our favorite example with a teddy
bear. Uh the context is you know
like what is the teddy bear basically
what is the mood of the teddy bear? What
do we want uh you know to do in order to
um like make our teddy bear happy and
then uh we we give some input regarding
where the story that we want to generate
is and then uh we give some constraints.
If you want some other example uh in the
LLMs that you query every day. So the
context could be um you know some
sentence that says you are chat GPT it
is uh you know we are October 10th uh it
is uh 4:44 p.m. So you set the setup.
The instructions can be uh basically
what the user queries alongside the
input and then constraints might be
things that you don't see as a user but
that might be um you know present in the
prompts given to the LLM such as safety
instructions for example do not generate
any contents that might lead to harm or
things like this. So you know every time
you see an input being fed to an LLM, I
think this projection into four these
four dimensions can be a good mental
model of seeing you know which pieces
correspond to what goal um in in that
structure.
Does that make sense?
Okay, great. So now that we know like
what kind of mindset we might have for
inputs to an LLM, let's see how we can
get an LLM to do what we want. And let's
see how we can get an LLM to do what we
want without tuning any weights. And we
can do so with a concept called in
context learning where the learning is a
bit of a term that is overloaded because
you don't actually learn anything with
respect to the weights of the LLM but
you can uh like distill some knowledge
inside of it um you know as part of the
context in order to do what you want. So
you distinguish two main categories of
in context learning. So there is one
category that is very simple you know in
mindset it's called zero shot. So
basically you don't give
anything other than your input um your
input query you know you just ask the
LLM to do what what you want to do and
then there is another uh school of
thought
learning where you give examples of
inputs and outputs to the LLM before
asking the input that you're interested
in. So in the case of teddy bears and
the bedtime stories. So you might, you
know, name your teddy bears. So maybe
you have a teddy teddy bear that's
called teddy and you generated a story.
So you put your query, you put the story
that you want to generate and you give
multiple such examples and let's say you
have another teddy bear that's called,
you know, Bob, you know, and then you
want to generate a story for Bob. So you
put all of these examples and you ask
the LLM to generate uh the story that
you're interested in and then this is
basically what we call a few shots
setting.
Okay, great. So now
um generally when you look at the
performance of the of the given u like
of the resulting task giving examples
tends to steer the LLM nicely into the
task that you're interested in just
because you have like given an idea to
the model of what you are looking for
and then it can use what it has learned
during its training process to connect
the dots and uh basically replicates
um and then uh but of course you need to
gather such examples. So this is costly
uh this will put some more uh tokens in
the context window. So you will need to
like more compute
uh but uh there is an interesting
trade-off here that we see in recent
models. So they're gaining more and more
reasoning capabilities which is why I
put the generally
um nuance in Italy here. So they're
generally better few shots but not
always because these days uh with this
like better models people have seen that
with um like basically making the
instruction better you could make the
performance of in context learning on
par or even better than if you provide
examples because basically when you
think of it when you provide examples
you constrain your model into given sets
of examples that are finite. So when you
are at inference time, let's say you
want to perform a task on a distribution
of data that has not been seen, it is
harder for the model to generalize
because it will try to align on what it
has seen in the context. Whereas if you
turn your instructions into something
that is more reasoning based, you
explain how to do the task with natural
language, it can use its reasoning
abilities to actually do it. And then
this is something that you see more and
more these days. Um so the literature on
this I think is still in in progress but
you have some papers like plan and solve
uh that I think came out recently and
that showed you know if you ask the LM
to plan itself and then solve something
uh it can have very good performance.
So yeah this is an interesting u this is
an interesting fact.
Okay great. So now that we have seen uh
basically the kinds of learning that we
have now we're going to see what we can
do to improve the quality of the
response. So there is this concept
called chain of thought where uh
researchers have seen that if you force
the model to come up with some rational
to some answer before actually giving it
it would give higher performance. So
this is what you what people call as
chain of thought. It's basically what's
led you to the answer. So here for
example if you uh you know ask yourself
you know how old is the teddy bear and
if you force the model to respond
directly with a number it might not be
able to do the connection as to exactly
why the teddy bear is a given age.
Whereas when you give the kind of full
chain of reasoning then it becomes clear
as to you know what led to that
response. So I think this is the main
mindset behind this technique
and uh basically this is something that
is that can be used in in context
learning. So if you give uh like few
shot examples you know how old were was
this teddy bear you give some number and
then you slightly change the query and
then based on the reasoning formatting
and then the response the LLM can adjust
the reasoning and the response
accordingly and it will force the model
to output some reasoning alongside the
response which shows an improvement in
um in basically metrics.
Okay, great. And then yeah, something
else that I want to say, you know, let's
say you are uh you want to do a task and
you want to do it well, you know, often
times you will always have some samples
that do not work and then for them you
you want to have debugging ability,
right? And usually when you debug with
LLMs, you don't debug like the old days,
you don't look at weights at at the
intrinsics of the LLM. What you want is
something more interpretable that comes
out of it in terms of tokens and usually
uh you know with these techniques you
can see the reasoning that the model had
before outputting a given response and
you can debug basically what went wrong.
So if you ask how old will will the bear
be next year and if in the chain of
thought it says hey we're in 2019
you know that somehow in your context
you know oh maybe I put the wrong dates
you know in there so you can like trace
back to you can do some root causing
very easily so it's also used for that
and you know exactly in the same way as
other techniques that increase the
number of tokens. This is a trade-off
that you have to manage that it will of
course take more time, you know, to
infer because you need to to generate
more tokens, but typically we're fine
with it.
Any questions on coot?
Okay, great. So, now let's take it one
step further.
Um so I want to introduce you know even
to make coot
even stronger. You can sample your model
several times look at the answers it
generates and then do some majority
voting to select the answer that was
predicted most of the times by a given
LLM. And this is what we call
self-consistency
where basically you sample responses
multiple times and then parse
the actual answer. So basically you kind
of factor out the whole reasoning and
then try to target the answer and then
by majority voting you can come up to an
answer in a more um robust way.
Yep.
Yep. So the question is do you need to
have some benchmark to know if it's
better and yes absolutely I think the
paper operates on top of all the
arithmetic and then mathematical based
ones and then I think one tangential
question to yours is how can you locate
the answer and then do majority majority
voting on it. So typically you can put
into the context some instruction that
says put the actual answer last. So you
can just like extract the last people I
think uh use regex based techniques
otherwise to extract the answer or you
could even think of using some other LLM
to extract the answer. So there is
always a way to kind of do it. Uh but
yeah to your point yes we need uh some
benchmark and then ground truth labels
to assert that this is indeed better.
Yeah. So the request here, so the
question is uh is it going to be sent to
the same request as example? So
typically you sample it in parallel. So
basically you ask your model exactly
what Ashin just mentioned. You sample
from the probability distribution of BOS
and whatever tokens you had the next
token and you do that in several other
uh kind of branches and you do that all
of that in parallel and then you kind of
parse the answer at the end of it. So
basically the latency of this process is
equal roughly to the maximum latency of
either parallel generation because you
can do all of this in parallel.
>> Yeah.
>> So so none of these go into the context
of each other. They're all done in
parallel and then you get final answer.
Okay. Great.
All good.
Okay. Great. So now that we have seen a
few prompting techniques uh I want to
cover together um tricks that people
have come up with at inference time to
make the generation as efficient as
possible. So
um and basically uh yeah so in modern
day models you have a lot of parameters
you want to generate a lot of tokens how
do you do it the most efficiently
possible. So I want to us to divide this
thought process into two parts. So we're
going to see you know what methods we
can come up with that give up that give
us increased efficiency on an exact
level. So you exactly do the same
computations as you were supposed to do
but you know in a more efficient way and
I put some um you know hints as to what
kind of techniques we're going to
explore. So you know let's take let's
try to look for techniques that avoid
redundancies.
Let's try to see what we could do to uh
manage the memory in the best way and
also let's try to see if we can uh
reformulate uh the equations inside the
LLM in a way that could simplify the the
generation in practice.
Then there is a second category that
we're going to explore as well uh that
is going to focus on what kind of
approximations it might be fine to do
and get a high quality answer uh at a le
at at a lesser cost uh but you know it
would be approximate. So we have you
know what kind of um variations we could
do on the architecture. Is there
something we could do on the embeddings
um to make them more efficient? And then
maybe on the token prediction side, is
there something we could uh do to make
it, you know, faster?
Does that sound good?
So, we have approximately 22 minutes.
We're going to try to go through all of
them um here. Okay. So I grouped the
categories of techniques into exact and
approximate techniques. Uh but actually
we're going to look at them in a grouped
manner. First looking at the attention
layer seeing what kind of techniques we
could um have there and then in a second
time in a second part we're going to
look at the output layer and then see
you know what we can do at the level of
token generation to make things uh you
know as as good as possible. Okay. So
let's start at the attention level.
So we have seen that uh you know for
every token you need the current token
to attend to the previous ones right in
this masked self attention. So let's say
you generate your sequence you are at a
given token. So let's say you know you
have generated a cute teddy bear and
then now you are at ease.
Now you have the query ease.
You will compute the key representation
and the and the value representation of
ease because of course you have to do
it. It's your current token. But we want
to have a way to reuse the past
computations we had done to compute the
key representation of the previous
tokens and the value representation of
the previous tokens.
Does that make sense as a goal? Does
everyone agree?
Okay.
And more precisely, basically, we want
to find a way for the key and value
matrices to be saved. And um you know
I'm not underlining the Q the Q part
here because of course the query
corresponding to the previous tokens are
not going to be of interest uh for the
the present token. So it's like the key
and value part.
Okay. So there is u like this concept of
KV cache where the goal is to store
these key and value matrices somewhere.
um
and reuse them directly from the cache.
So like what I just mentioned here, you
know, when you want to compute a given
token, you would reuse the key and the
value directly from the cache instead of
computing it again. So yeah, so
um yeah, so this is basically um you
know representation of what we just
mentioned here.
Um yeah, does that make sense?
Okay, awesome.
So, what else we could could we do? Oh,
yeah.
Yeah, great question. So, during
training, do we do KV caching? I would
say during uh training, you have this
concept of teacher forcing where you put
all your inputs and pass it all together
at once. So this concept of KV caching
caching doesn't even come up. Uh yeah.
Yeah. But great point. Yeah. Yep.
>> Yep. Yep. Yes. So the question was uh
you know what is the point of all this?
We want to just reuse uh like the
computations that were already done and
then your answer is yes. Spot on.
Any other questions?
Okay great. So now that we have seen you
know that we could cache these
quantities. So what else could we do? So
is there something from last week's
lecture that we could reuse? you know,
maybe something that reduces the amount
of cash, you know, the key and value.
Do we have some techniques
sparse attention? Um,
yeah, that could be that could be, but
not here. Like, let's say you're not
you're attending to everyone and you
focus on the number of keys and values.
Is there a a way to reduce this number?
So just to recap, we have here I'm
operating in the context of multi- head
detention which is you have your H
heads. So you have H number of query
projections, H key projections, H value
projections. Is is there any technique
from last week that we could reuse that
could reduce this number?
Yeah, I heard it. Yeah, group query
attention. Yeah, exactly. So we had this
um you know concept of grouping keys and
values together uh where basically the
general formulation is called group
query attention where you group these
and then the external values h and one
denote respectively the full multi head
intention and then multi-query attention
and then in uh modern day LLM's uh like
a lot of papers they use uh GQA
uh with with some uh group that is
sensible value. Yeah. So this is also
something we can do.
Okay. Great. And now I'm going to go a
little bit into the hardware side of
things.
So if we were to store the cache for all
these values in a naive way, you know,
at inference time. So let's say you
receive so let's say I'm an inference
server I receive queries from multiple
users
and let's say I receive a query one and
I receive a query two um you know a
naive way of storing the key and and
value um you know matrices would be in
reserving a pro a portion of the memory
at the beginning that correspond to the
entire context length.
because you don't know you know where
you're going to stop right your decoding
because you stop your decoding when you
hit the EOS token so you would have like
this whole block of size uh you know
context length like maximum context
length that could be reserved so one
observation is that it leads to a lot of
waste so let's say if your context
length is of size like 2k you have 2k
reserved for a given uh you know request
2k Okay, there. So at any given time
like let's say you want to get more
requests, you want to serve more
requests, your memory will very quickly
not have enough space to uh accommodate
uh them.
Does this constraints or this challenge
make sense?
Yep.
Okay. And then there is this paper uh
that uh that is called page detention
and it defines several um like
quantities. So there is this like
reserved quantity internal fragmentation
and external fragmentation. Internal
fragmentation is basically the space
that is being reserved by the model to
complete the request and the reserved
spot is the subset of it that
corresponds to tokens that were actually
being used. So it's the kind of space
that's actually used internal
fragmentation. There is nothing in there
but this was reserved. an external
fragmentation. It's the memory uh
management system that doesn't
necessarily put one uh you know block
one after another but has its own way of
allocating uh memory blocks. So it might
give some other gaps and they came up
with a system that is called a page
detention uh that is um you know
powering uh one inference
package called the VLM
that uh solves this issue by mapping uh
like the generation process by blocks of
fixed size. So instead of uh
allocating a whole portion of the memory
to answer a given request, it breaks it
down by smaller chunks. So I think the
paper takes uh like a value of 16 for
blocks. So as you can see, let's say you
are in your generation process and you
have used a given row, you would just
start using another row without
um you know wasting more space than
that.
And then you have some dictionary that
maps token position indices to uh to
basically their their cache values. So
there is like a smart way of managing it
and they show that it reduces
fragmentation by quite a lot.
Yeah.
Okay. Great.
Now let's do something else with this KV
cache. So uh we just saw that you know
you have your internal representation of
your token and you project it into query
key and value and then key and value is
actually something that is of a
dimension that is like non-negligible
and you need to store uh each copies of
it in each transformer block. So you
have many of these uh vectors that you
need to keep track of and is there a way
to make that representation somehow more
compact
and this is a topic that uh DeepS has um
you know tried to tackle in a concept
called um I think it was called
multi-latent
attention.
We're going to see uh so you know let's
look at the vanilla case you know if you
are in multi head detention then for a
given representation of a token you have
h projection matrices that turn it into
a key
does everyone agree with that
the kind of uh self attention formula
you know you have a projection matrix w
k for keys that will project the token
representation into some key and you
have h heads,
you have h such projections and you have
h such resulting embeddings that you
need to store in your cache cuz you have
that for keys, you have that for values,
that's a lot of um vectors to store and
these keys and values they are uh you
know
quite long as well. Uh so let's see if
we can like um make it smaller.
What multi- latent attention does is
that it factorizes these um you know
projection matrix into an intermediary
space that is of lower dimension than
the space of keys.
You have a first transformation that
reduces the dimension and then another
one that decompresses it.
So this is the first
u operation kind of that they did in
order to make the reput representation
more compact.
But they did something else that is very
smart. They said that the compression
matrix
could be shared across keys and values.
which says for a given token
representation
the cache that you need to store for
keys and for values is the same
and then you would have u you know still
different matrices here for the
decompression part to like actually
learn different representations for a
key and value. But you know one
um simplification here has been to like
share it for like across keys and values
and even better share it across the h
heads. So instead of having h such
embeddings you have just one
uh and then you do that you know for key
you do that for value. So at the end of
it for every transformer block you have
a single representation per token.
Does that make sense?
So not only
you have you know less things to store
the deep sev2 paper also showed a
performance improvement that it's uh
kind of credited like some
regularization
um consequence of doing so. So it it
learns representations that are maybe
more useful and shared across keys and
values. So you know apparently there is
also um performance benefits to it that
is not just hardware based.
Okay great. So now we have seen some
trick. Oh yeah.
Yeah. So the question is do you tune the
low rank dimension? So the dimension
itself is a design choice. It's fixed.
So the question is is it the same uh
like lower dimension for everyone? So
the dimension size is fixed and is the
same for everyone I think. So but it's a
design choice. Yeah, you you could have
different ones but I think in practice
it's it might be the same one.
>> Yep.
Any other questions?
Okay, great. So now we have less than 10
minutes. We are going to cover
techniques that operate at the output
token level. Um and then start with a
concept called speculative dec decoding.
That is um kind of a very interesting
method that uses some smaller model to
help the generation of a bigger model
and then uses some scheme that makes the
distribution output match the one of the
target one. So it uses a combination of
tricks of using like a smaller model to
generate things and then gates it with
some mathematical based properties to
ensure we get a distribution that looks
like the one of the big model.
So here's what is the mind like here's
the mindset of it. So let's just come
back to our favorite example about teddy
bears.
So what you do is that you ask a a
smaller model uh that we that the paper
calls draft to generate next words. So
you have like my teddy bear you know
what could be next words. So you have
one pass you know you find token is you
fit token is here again you find cute
and smart since the LLM is small this is
typically done faster than with the big
LLM.
And then once you have all of these, you
put the tokens that are predicted by the
smaller LLM all as input to the target
uh LLM that is like the bigger model
like the one that you use to generate
probability distributions for each of
them.
And then we're going to see that by
having some rule on the output
distribution of each of these tokens,
you can simulate
a distribution, a probability
distribution of each token of each next
token that's um kind of looks like the
one of the target models.
So here's basically how it goes. Um so
it looks at the probability of the the
token that the draft model has
predicted. So if the probability of the
draft model is bigger than the one of
the draft model in the draft model's
output distribution then you just accept
the token. Otherwise you have some
acceptance rejection mechanism that
either accepts the token or rejects it.
And uh you know let's say everything is
accepted then in a single pass you were
able to advance you know by way more
tokens
um and then if it fails then basically
you resume the process of generation
from that code token onwards with some
uh adjustments on the distribution.
So one question that you might ask from
all of this you know this looks like a
recipe like why is that matching the
target distribution.
So if you start from the law of total
probability and write each term with
these quantities
then you will find the target
distribution at the end. So it's an
exercise that I encourage you to do and
the to the paper that is attached to the
slide here demonstrates it in like just
a few lines. So it's a very simple
proof. Uh and I think it's a very very
interesting one.
Does that does that make sense? Yep.
Yeah. So I think it's Yeah. The question
is is that rejection sampling? Yep.
So, some of you might be familiar with
it already.
Does that make sense?
Yeah. And then one thing that I didn't
say is that why did we even put the last
token here? You know, we put all the
draft tokens, but also the last one that
was predicted because by doing a single
forward pass with all these draft
tokens, you get for free the probability
distribution of the token that comes
after that that you can then just sample
from Q k + one.
So like just to give some summary of the
rational
um doing a single pass is like as
expensive as doing one pass at a time
because at inference time you are memory
bound like in other words
uh computations are not the limiting
factor. It's basically the memory that
will bottleneck your computation. So you
want to do it on a smaller model and
then on the big model you want to
compute all of these probability
distributions at once.
Does that make sense?
Okay, great.
And then I want to talk about one last
technique that is called multi-token
prediction. It's the same. So by the
way, this previous technique was called
speculative decoding.
And then this one is basically doing the
same but so it's doing exactly a
different thing but the draft model is
embedded in the same model which is very
powerful. So basically it's a model that
uh attaches multiple heads on top of the
representation of the last decoder.
And the process here is that at training
time, it doesn't do next word
prediction. It does multi-word
prediction. And at test time, the draft
model is all your heads. And your uh
main model is just the first heads. So
you have like all your draft uh tokens
that you then feed back to the first
head and then do accept acceptance and
rejection. So the paper does it in a
greedy way. So doesn't do it with this
like formula because since the
architecture and then the objective
function has changed. you don't have
this like nice property of finding again
the like next token predictions
distribution but you have like a slight
variation of it and uh yeah so like the
interesting note out of the multi-token
prediction is the change in objective
function and then second the um the fact
that the draft model and the target
model are basically embedded in the same
one
so don't have to like separate the two
and Um yeah so you do remember these
slides we have explored techniques that
can remedy each of these aspects. So
yeah I highly recommend you know taking
a look at the associated papers as well.
And with that thank you very much.